A Guide to the Papers of F. Scott Fitzgerald, [1915]-1971, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Correspondence
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to F. P. Adams, 1920 September 11, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:28)
    Fitzgerald is seeking out information about a columnist, either "H. O. or O. H. McIntyre." #6177
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to [Ruth A. Conley], [ca. 1920-1925], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:29)
    Responding to a teen-age fan who wrote a letter after reading This Side of Paradise, Fitzgerald responds: "I will be at the corner of Boston Common on Monday Evening, April 22nd, 1930 wearing a red rose as you suggest, a quiet suit of royal purple and red whit and blue suspenders." In a postscript, Fitzgerald seriously thanks her and writes that he was "pleased and touched." #6177
  - [F.] Scott Fitz[gerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1921] September 12, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope and enclosed photograph (Box-folder 1:30)
    Fitzgerald, in Venice, came across the boat "Sturtevant" named after Ruth's brother, Albert Sturtevant. Mentions how the officers of the boat were curious about Albert. A biographical note regarding the death of Albert Sturtevant reads: "On 15 February 1918, while flying an escort mission with another plane of his unit, the two American were jumped by a flight of 10 German planes. Sturtevant's companion recognized the hopelessness of the 5-to-l odds and escaped to safety, but Sturtevant gamely fought it out with the enemy. When last seen, Ensign Sturtevant was hit and crippled, falling toward the sea. For his heroic actions, he was awarded the Navy Cross posthumously." #6177
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to Joseph Hergesheimer, [ca. 1922], ANS copy, 1 p. inscription in The Beautiful and the Damned (Box-folder 1:31)
    "For Joseph Hergeshiemer [sic] from F. Scott Fitzgerald who thinks he will find no warmth in this cold hell. St Paul." Barrett PS 3511.I9 B4 1922 c.4
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to Miss Paxton, [ca. 1922-1924], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:32)
    Fitzgerald turns down an invitation to speak at the University of Illinois jokingly because the University wouldn't want "a collapsed novelist wandering wildly over the campus" but seriously because he is "absolutely incapable through constitutional stage fright." He is honored by the invitation, though. #6177-c
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to Mr. Maurice, [ca. 1923 February], ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:33)
    Apologizes for his inability to write a review for Sherwood Anderson's new book [Many Marriages] because "it's an amazing book and affected me profoundly." His first attempt at a review was "the worst drivel ever launched." [Zelda] decided it to be "criminal to hand it in." Anderson's book needs the "most careful consideration else one is temped [sic] to say the wildest things about it." Admits it is the first time he can remember having failed to live up to his word "on a thing like this." #6177
  - [F.] Scott Fitz[gerald] to George Northrop, [ca. 1926?], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:34)
    In Provence, France for their third summer, and would like Northrop to dine with them. Fitzgerald working on a chapter for a new novel [Tender is the Night]. #6177-e
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to Mr. [James V.?] Barret, [ca. 1927-1928?], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:35)
    Writes an anecdote about a priest giving a form of Absolution to a boy. Concludes by saying the reason he hasn't written many stories is that he has "been working on a novel [Tender is the Night] for several years." #6177-d
  - [F.] Scott Fitzgerald to Gelett, [ca. 1930?], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:36)
    Cannot attend a [literary conference?] because his wife is sick and he has to take his mother to Carlsbad. But [Ernest] Hemingway and John Peale Bishop should be there. #6177
  - [F.] Scott Fitzgerald to [Alfred] Dashiell, [ca. 1931 June], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:37)
    Accepts offer to do article [Echoes of the Jazz Age], and will send it to [Scribner's] by early July. #6177
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to Dayton Kohler, 1932 January 25, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:38)
    Apologizes for late response because just after he received Kohler's letter he "left France for Switzerland in terrible confusion because of the sickness of [his] wife." Delighted with article Kohler wrote about him, which covered him with a "soothing oil" and made him feel "more important" than he has felt "for ages." Writing a novel [Tender is the Night] which should justify everything Kohler wrote about him. Fitzgerald feels he is "forgotten by the whole new generation which has grown up" since he published his last book in 1926. #6177
  - [F.] Scott Fitzgerald to Frank [?], 1933 October 11, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:39)
    Offers thanks for writing Fitzgerald about the article on Ring Lardner, [Ring, The New Republic]. #6177
  - [F.] Scott [Fitzgerald] to [John] Dos [Passos], 1934 October 24, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:40)
    Responds to a letter from Dos Passos that disturbed him, but remains glad that Dos Passos remains "in touch with Ernest [Hemingway] during this trouble." Thanks Dos Passos for the long letter and asks that his "love" be given to Katie [Dos Passos]. Fitzgerald is writing from the hospital at John's Hopkins where Dos Passos spent some time, and the "nurses and attendants" remember him affectionately. On verso seems to be a grocery list in unknown hand: "M. Fish, asperin, soap, alcohol, tooth paste, new cap,..." #5950
  - [F.] Scott [Fitzgerald] to Mary Brown, 1934 December 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:41)
    Asks Mary Brown a favor although she "did not duly acknowledge" the books which he autographed for her. Requests that Mary Brown find a job for his secretary [Alyce Wootton] in the advertising department, as Zelda and Fitzgerald are "very fond of her." #6177-a
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to Joe [Hergesheimer], [ca. 1934], ALS xerox copy, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:42)
    Fitzgerald perplexed that "someone didn't like the book." Stresses that the actress in the book [Tender is the Night] is only a "catalytic agent." Asks Joe to read from the middle: "Sometime will you open it at the middle, perhaps at page 155, + read on for five or ten minutes-?" Fitzgerald would like Tender is the Night, the "favorite" among his books, to have another chance with someone he sincerely admires. Original inscribed in Tender is the Night, PS 3511.I9 T4 1934 copy 4. #6177-g
  - [F.] Scott Fitzgerald to Horace F. Simon, 1935 January 30, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with autograph corrections (Box-folder 1:43)
    Fitzgerald writes a letter of introduction for Alyce Wootton, "a very intelligent, competent and pretty Baltimore girl." Fitzgerald "boasted" to Wootton of having been classmates with Simon at Princeton. #6177-a
  - [F.] Scott Fitz[gerald] to Alycia [Wootton], 1935 February 28, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:44)
    Admitting that he hasn't "touched liquor for a month," Fitzgerald tries to remember what he has done in finding Wootton a job, as he seems to have forgotten much of what he did. Then he criticizes her manuscript: "It won't do, Alyce. It is in part too personal and in part not personal enough." In reference to her description of a woman's tonsils, Fitzgerald responds: the description "gives a revolting picture of the lady's throat." Tells her the stories about "the writer [Fitzgerald] living in a dressing gown isn't sufficiently new or startling," which is "sad but true." #6177-a
  - [F.] Scott Fitz[gerald] to Charles MacArthur, 1935 March 2, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:45)
    A letter of introduction for [Alyce Wootton] for a position as script girl: "I know you could count on a hard worker and a most attractive lady indeed." #6177-a
  - [F.] Scott Fitz[gerald] to Alycia [Wootton], 1935 May 14, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:46)
    Cannot recall any "Jack Williams" that went to Princeton with him. Tells Alyce that "the establishment here is breaking up" and that he has to go south to recuperate. Claims he doesn't drink any more "(4 mos.)" and that she would like him better. States that he put a "tail" on Wootton's husband and has found out that "he is running around with a lovely high yellow girl named Sally Washington." Jokingly ends with "Scottie has leprosy. Mrs. Owens is in prison for assault and battery." #6177-a
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to John Dos Passos, 1936 September 21, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:47)
    Fitzgerald writes that he just finished reading "the Book" which "interferes" with everything he does. Discusses his conversation about a "Cuban boy." Has not read "Mary French" [character in Dos Passos Trilogy] which Fitzgerald heard was the "best of all." Reading has been the most exciting thing to happen to him between the time he broke his shoulder and the "blowing up of Gerald and Sallie in the Alcazar." In pencil beneath note he writes "dictated- I have a cracked shoulder" and "God help us!" in reference to "Margle." #5950
  - [F.] Scott Fitz[gerald] to "Allien" [Isabel] Owens, 1937 October 8, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:48)
    Long paragraph about Scottie "seeming happy" in Los Angeles, where she had "much more poise... than during her lamentable career as the Belle of Baltimore." Discusses the near completion of Three Comrades. Asks a favor, that his business papers and scrap books be sent out to him in California. Likes it in California, and believes he will be very good at script writing, which is "most often like fitting together a very interesting picture puzzle." #6177-c
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to [?], n.d., ANS copy, 1 p. inscription in The Beautiful and the Damned (Box-folder 1:49)
    Fitzgerald wrote: "The phrase 'Beautiful but Dumb' was this book's contribution to its time...It has awful spots but some good ones. I was trying to learn." Barrett PS 3511.I9 B4 1922c c.3
  - Zelda Fitzgerald to [John] Dos [Passos], n.d., n.d., ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:50)
    In a deeply religious letter, Zelda concerns herself with "the salvation" of her friends. Zelda corrects her friends, stating that the "commandments of Christ" were not learned at "Princeton and Yale." Then she demands Dos Passos to stop calling her "a man-eating night-blooming [tarantulus syringa] just for the sake of the mode." She writes that Scottie is "the spirit of the truth" and if [Sheila Lewis] "or the absence of cognac in your coffee or the [restless] usage of war make you cry or cause you to think with every one of the dead, call her up. She will be able to solve things..." Zelda continues to write her book and continues to tell people about God. 5950
  - Scribner's Magazine to [F.] Scott Fitzgerald, 1931 July 21, cablegram, 1 item (Box-folder 1:51)
    Scribner's asks Fitzgerald if article [Echoes of the Jazz Age] has been sent, and if not, to please rush it. See Fitzgerald to Dashiell, [ca. 1931 June] for letter regarding article. #6177
- Series III: Miscellaneous Documents
  - Autograph envelope to Ruth Sturtevant with news clipping regarding Fitzgerald prank, [1916 March 1], 1 item (Box-folder 1:52)
    News clipping entitled, Stunning Blond Stuns 'U' Men: F. Scott Fitzgerald in Feminine Attire Invades Fraternity Ballroom. Also includes a page from a 1916 desk calendar for the month of February. #6177-c
  - This Side of Paradise, title page and "Author's Apology," [1920 May], DS, 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:53)
    Fitzgerald composed this one-page note to be tipped into copies of the third printing of This Side of Paradise and distributed at the May 1920 convention of the American Bookseller's Association. The "Author's Apology" includes Fitzgerald's theory of writing: "My whole theory of writing I can sum up in one sentence: An author ought to write for the youth of his own generation, the critics of the next, and the schoolmasters of ever afterward." #6177
  - Birth announcement of Scotty Fitzgerald, 1921 October 26, D, 1 item (Box-folder 1:54)
  - Three promotional photographs of F. Scott Fitzgerald, n.d., 3 items (Box-folder 1:55)